<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Releases on Sabayon Linux </title>
    <link>https://www.sabayon.org/categories/releases/</link>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <author>Sabayon Linux</author>
    <rights>Copyright (c) 2015, Sabayon Linux; all rights reserved.</rights>
    <updated>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UTC</updated>
     
    <item>
      <title>Sabayon and Funtoo Linux Merge Projects</title>
      <link>https://www.sabayon.org/article/joining-funtoo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Sabayon Linux</author>
      <guid>https://www.sabayon.org/article/joining-funtoo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/2420543/99854407-0d606d00-2b85-11eb-9e17-4c066ee9e0e5.jpg width=320&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabayon is about to move on to its next chapter. We are glad to announce that we are about to join forces with &lt;a href=&#34;http://funtoo.org/&#34;&gt;Funtoo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you heard it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a special moment for our development team, as two strongly Gentoo focused communities are joining together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Funtoo Linux is a community-developed Linux meta-distribution based upon Gentoo Linux. Funtoo Linux is optimized for the best possible performance on the latest Intel and AMD hardware. Funtoo is led by Daniel Robbins, the creator of Gentoo Linux, and actively developed by the Funtoo community”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funtoo shines for additional QA layers, proven reliability, and incredible performance setup out of the box, plus the wonderful metatools and Kits ecosystem. Funtoo has a strong community with a solid background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By joining together forces, years of experience, knowledge, and tooling, we will be able to deliver the best Linux experience also in a binary format, stronger, and together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will mutually contribute to each others’ projects, actually merging our development teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we are bringing together our knowledge base and toolset to build new ecosystems and projects behind the same umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn’t a final decision yet on how we will move forward, but we will promise to keep everyone in the loop as the situation evolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome &lt;a href=&#34;http://funtoo.org/&#34;&gt;Funtoo&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabayon team&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sabayon project is rebranding to MocaccinoOS</title>
      <link>https://www.sabayon.org/article/sabayon-is-rebranding/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Sabayon Linux</author>
      <guid>https://www.sabayon.org/article/sabayon-is-rebranding/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Howdy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been quite a long time since we have made an official post, so here we are, almost at the end of 2020 discussing Sabayon&amp;rsquo;s future and upcoming changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be frank, we are nearing the end of Sabayon as we’ve known it, and we are looking back at what was great, and what could be improved upon. We haven’t been the best at communication - there has been radio silence for almost a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean we weren’t active, or that we’ve abandoned the project… on the contrary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For us this has been a very busy year. We have been building up a new toolset for upcoming releases, and trying to innovate and renew the project for the future. There are big changes coming soon, and now is the right time for us to finally share what’s coming next with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sabayon-project-is-rebranding-to-mocaccinoos-https-www-mocaccino-org&#34;&gt;Sabayon project is rebranding to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mocaccino.org/&#34;&gt;MocaccinoOS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/2420543/99854417-118c8a80-2b85-11eb-8b6a-1567203d306b.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image4&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This won’t be our final logo, we’re looking for contributors for artwork!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migration to MocaccinoOS will work from any flavour of Sabayon, and we will keep pushing updates on the Sabayon Linux main repo until MocaccinoOS is fully bootstrapped and officially released to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment of writing, MocaccinoOS is not ready yet for daily usage, and we suggest you do not attempt to migrate any machine you rely upon just yet. That said, we welcome everyone to test out Mocaccino on any spare hardware you might have, or in virtual machines and provide feedback on where we might improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabayon users will keep receiving updates on the sabayonlinux.org repositories, but the sabayon-weekly repositories have been frozen already. &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.sabayon.org/index.php?title=En:Entropy#enabling_a_different_repository_or_mirror&#34;&gt;See here for instructions for switching between these repositories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-package-manager&#34;&gt;New package manager&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2019 we have been working on a new brand package manager, called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mudler/luet&#34;&gt;Luet&lt;/a&gt;, which will eventually replace Entropy. It is designed to solve some of the limitations and issues that we have observed while working with Entropy.
Building packages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entropy has proven to work well over the years, but it had some big limitations on the maintainer side. For example, it needs a central server to build packages, and packages have been maintained by hand for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might sound fine, but this approach has several drawbacks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No easy way to have reproducible builds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No easy way to have divergent packages (e.g. community repositories)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No native distributed compilation (without resorting to something like distcc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The build server is a single point of failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only one person can work on the build server at a time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Special knowledge and tools needed around infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No way to track changes on the build server in a human readable way (e.g. to backtrack problems)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-power-of-containers&#34;&gt;The power of containers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/2420543/99854507-3bde4800-2b85-11eb-9bc3-4eac5617a16f.jpg width=320&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address the above mentioned issues, Luet provides an abstraction layer on top of container technologies, like Docker, which let us build packages without having a central server building packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images used to build packages are shared via Docker registries, so they can be reused later on, not only by our main build infrastructure, but also by anyone that wishes to build their own packages against the same environment - or who just wants to inspect the build environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our new package manager solves these disadvantages. We can run reproducible builds, across a wide range of build infrastructure, and the process is much more open to contributors, or for folks to build their own packages using the same tools we use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-luet-comes-to-play&#34;&gt;Where Luet comes to play&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why not use just Docker to build packages?
While this might sound familiar, this is even more familiar to us. We have been using Docker into our infrastructure for more than 5 years already for building ISO images and community repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encountered a few pitfalls of using Docker directly, which have been addressed in Luet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No first class representation of a package definition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s up to you to maintain reverse dependencies of docker images, which images need updating when a base image changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Images can be based on only a single base image; you can’t have package A coming from Image B and C unless you handle that manually.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No structured way to represent a tree of related images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/2420543/99854416-0fc2c700-2b85-11eb-8823-544459b77423.png&#34; alt=&#34;image3&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luet provides an abstraction layer on top of the container image layer to make the package a first class construct. A package definition and all its dependencies are translated by Luet to Dockerfiles which can then be built anywhere that docker runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dependency-resolution&#34;&gt;Dependency resolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To resolve the dependency tree Luet uses a SAT solver and no database. It is responsible for calculating the dependencies of a package and to prevent conflicts. The Luet core is still young, but it has a comprehensive test suite that we use to validate any future changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pluggable-system&#34;&gt;Pluggable system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luet can be extended in 2 ways, by extensions and plugins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extensions expand Luet featureset horizontally, so for example, “luet geniso” will allow you to build an iso using luet, without this needing to be part of the luet core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugins instead are expanding Luet vertically by hooking into internal events. Plugins and Extensions can be written in any language, bash included!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;musl-branch&#34;&gt;Musl branch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are building a Musl LFS branch. It is completely from scratch and has just a few packages, which you can see &lt;a href=&#34;https://packages.mocaccino.org/mocaccino-musl-universe&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://packages.mocaccino.org/mocaccino-micro&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; . The big advantage with Luet here, is that you can build and fork the entire tree and build it locally without any target chroot - Luet will take care of that for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;statically-built&#34;&gt;Statically built&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, Luet is written entirely in Go and comes as a single static binary. This has a few advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to recover. You can use luet to bootstrap the system entirely from the ground-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Package manager has no dependencies on the packages that it installs. There is no chance of breaking the package manager by installing a conflicting package, or uninstalling one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Portable - it can run on any architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s not all, there’s even more exciting news still to come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;call-for-contributors&#34;&gt;Call for contributors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are always looking to grow our community, and to share knowledge and experiences with Linux and computer technology, don’t hesitate to engage and reach us via &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mocaccino.org/community/&#34;&gt;slack and discourse&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;call-for-artwork-contributions&#34;&gt;Call for artwork contributions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we are rebranding into MocaccinoOS we are in need of new artwork! If you have ideas and want to contribute, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mocaccino.org/community/&#34;&gt;reach to us over slack!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sabayon is still around!</title>
      <link>https://www.sabayon.org/article/sabayon-is-back-and-kicking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Sabayon Linux</author>
      <guid>https://www.sabayon.org/article/sabayon-is-back-and-kicking/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-re-still-here&#34;&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re still here!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re sure some of you are wondering when the next release will happen,
or if we&amp;rsquo;re even still alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, rest assured, we&amp;rsquo;re here and doing all kinds of work on Sabayon to make
the best release possible for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;abbr title=&#34;Too long; didn&#39;t read&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/abbr&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meltdown and Spectre&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new release strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new build infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;funding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;moving-ecosystem&#34;&gt;Moving ecosystem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot going on in the world of Linux.
2017 was a huge year for Linux dev!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graphics drivers were exploding in size and features, several kernel releases,
wine hit 3.0rc, new hardware and drivers (some amazing, some disappointing),
compilers changed, KDE and Gnome grew by leaps and bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We switched to FFmpeg upon user requests for software compatibility,
bumped X.org with AMDGPU, took on the bleeding edge
without falling into the chaos of going unstable,
and we&amp;rsquo;ve even done some internal restructuring to lower our cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meltdown-and-spectre&#34;&gt;Meltdown and Spectre&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re looking to patch Meltdown and Spectre bugs where we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all that is said and done we are now looking to sync up
with the rest of the Linux community.
Gentoo has moved on and made several underlying changes
and we plan to follow suit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is mostly stuff on the underlying portion of Sabayon,
but results in a lot of rebuilt packages.
This can be a rather painful experience,
but we&amp;rsquo;re committed to getting it done and passing on the finished
and polished product to our end users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is a moving target.
Even so, we want to find the best place to make a snapshot to show you,
our users, that we have you covered!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-team&#34;&gt;New team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017 the team behind Sabayon grew.
Now we have a test team, a webmaster and motivated &amp;ldquo;old dogs&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So expect more changes to happen ;-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;optiz0r - &lt;abbr title=&#34;Sabayon Community Repositories&#34;&gt;SCR&lt;/abbr&gt; maintainer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;darksurf - Testing team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ryuno-Ki - Webmaster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlik - Overlay and binary package maintainer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus of the webmaster will be on the website first, then turning to the
wiki before looking on improving the forums. Any help is very welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested in joining the Sabayon team? Everybody is welcome!
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sabayon.org/chat/&#34;&gt;Contact us on IRC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;freenode.net #sabayon-dev&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have ideas,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bugs.sabayon.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Hosted%20Services&#34;&gt;feel free to share them with us&lt;/a&gt; :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-release-strategy&#34;&gt;New release strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly it turned out that our
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sabayon.org/release/latest-monthly-release-sabayon-1611/#changes&#34;&gt;current release cycle&lt;/a&gt;
were not sustainable given the limited number of people available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new official strategy is to follow
the Ubuntu cycle of April and November of every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stable releases will be paired with LTS kernels (though as always,
newer kernels will be available for those who want them).
Monthly and daily built ISOs will still be offered, but are not guaranteed to
be thoroughly tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-build-infrastructure&#34;&gt;New build infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017 the Sabayon build infrastructure was moved
to more powerful and reliable servers.
This also allows more flexibility for testing significant upcoming changes
in Gentoo without affecting the daily running of Sabayon operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;funding-situation&#34;&gt;Funding situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provide Sabayon to you free of charge,
but sadly the infrastructure we need to build it does cost us money.
We&amp;rsquo;ve recently restructured to cut costs and continue the project.
Any &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sabayon.org/donate/&#34;&gt;donations&lt;/a&gt; would be greatly appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We accept the following cryptocurrencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;abbr title=&#34;Bitcoin&#34;&gt;BTC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;abbr title=&#34;Bitcoin Cash&#34;&gt;BCH&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;abbr title=&#34;Ethereum&#34;&gt;ETH&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;abbr title=&#34;LiteCoin&#34;&gt;LTC&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;abbr title=&#34;Monero&#34;&gt;XMR&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;abbr title=&#34;Neo&#34;&gt;NEO&lt;/abbr&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that the team wishes you a New Year 2018!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep rocking!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Critical Incident - 2018-01-15</title>
      <link>https://www.sabayon.org/article/sabayon_2018_critical_announcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Sabayon Linux</author>
      <guid>https://www.sabayon.org/article/sabayon_2018_critical_announcement/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;critical-incident-2018-01-15&#34;&gt;Critical Incident - 2018-01-15&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened&#34;&gt;What happened?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the weekly update of package repositories yesterday, some scripts
and binaries that were only meant to be installed on our internal
infrastructure were incorrectly pushed to all users. The updates that
contained the offending content were only available for a short window
(less than 24 hours) and have now been removed from all official mirrors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The update contained an experimental cryptocurrency miner and its
configuration files. The intention was to leverage the idle CPU time on Sabayon
infrastructure hosts to increase funding for the project via a Monero
wallet. This was setup on one of the internal development repositories for testing
and accidentally promoted to the main Sabayon package repositories in error by
another member of staff who was unaware of its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very sorry that this has happened and we apologize for any inconvenience
it may have caused you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-you-tell-if-you-ve-been-affected&#34;&gt;How can you tell if you&amp;rsquo;ve been affected?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your systems updated the package repositories (e.g. using &amp;ldquo;equo update&amp;rdquo;,
or from the rigo background auto updater),
between 2018-01-14 20:30 UTC and 2018-01-15 18:00 UTC,
you may find a miner process named &amp;ldquo;sd&amp;rdquo; running on your system. This process
may have been using up to 100% of one CPU core since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also see a hidden file at &amp;ldquo;/etc/entropy/.infra_machine&amp;rdquo; was was intended
to limit the affects to only the infrastructure hosts, but which was inadvertantly
created on all machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-you-clean-up&#34;&gt;How can you clean up?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either killing the miner &amp;ldquo;sd&amp;rdquo; process if present, or restarting your computer
will stop this activity. If present on your system the &amp;ldquo;.infra_machine&amp;rdquo; hidden
file can be safely deleted with &amp;ldquo;sudo rm /etc/entropy/.infra_machine&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No further cleanup is required as the miner scripts were
not made to be persistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As sign of good faith we will be donating the equivalent amount of money
generated by the miners to charity.
At time of writing, this is approximately valued at 5 Euro.
You can independently check the value of the wallet and any transactions
relating to it by entering the wallet address
(49oFnBbQbwXEJ8eTcWxVDb12Sbktn9XHQ6ysezutij4xGbXLYaygeDNTWEKoae9E4fMedQJy5g9QMQk1Hy7YuB7HHaJSGdg)
at &lt;a href=&#34;https://moneropool.com&#34;&gt;moneropools&lt;/a&gt;.
The chosen charity will be announced on the blog once all mining activity
has slowed/stopped and the final amount generated is known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happened in part because the Sabayon package build process involves
manual activity by different staff members on the same server. We have already
been working for some time on further automating these processes to remove the
manual work on servers, and make the build processes more transparent to users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/u/1/112606733744204696895/posts/fVaWrXkHUsn&#34;&gt;Joe Cuchac&lt;/a&gt;
for bringing this issue to our attention earlier today, and to nks0ne, iTitou,
and Mr-Hide from IRC for their assistance in tracking down the source.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AMDGPU and Linux growing pains</title>
      <link>https://www.sabayon.org/article/amdgpu_20170624/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2017 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
      <author>Sabayon Linux</author>
      <guid>https://www.sabayon.org/article/amdgpu_20170624/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may be aware that FGRLX is dead and AMDGPU-PRO is the new
proprietary (hybrid) driver. Some of you may still be using the radeon driver
on AMD HD7XXX or R9 2XX (SI/CIK) video cards. This will most likely change
in the future. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;amp;px=AMDGPU-Radeon-Switching-CIK&#34;&gt;Methods of switching are being discussed for 4.13 kernel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;amdgpu-pro&#34;&gt;AMDGPU-PRO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been a few questions I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed about having issues with HDMI
audio over AMDGPU and/or people asking when AMDGPU-PRO will be be supported.
I&amp;rsquo;m here to say AMDGPU-PRO isn&amp;rsquo;t coming to Gentoo/Sabayon, but for good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differences in AMDGPU and AMDGPU-PRO, once complete, will be minimal.
AMDGPU-PRO is a &amp;ldquo;hybrid&amp;rdquo; driver meaning paritially open and closed source.
Nearly everything in AMDGPU-PRO will be in AMDGPU open source. AMDGPU-PRO
will be geared for supporting FirePRO cards in workstations and tested
to support things such as solidworks and other business software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are some gaps in support. Where PRO supports Freesync, HDMI 2.0,
HDMI Audio, OpenCL, etc., the AMDGPU driver will eventually attain all that
through what is known as Display Code (DC) or DAL/HAL (Display/Hardware abstraction
layer). The old DAL was just as it sounds, an abastraction layer. This
could basically be summed up as a middle man layer that needed translation
to be native or direct communication with the hardware. This is not allowed in
the Linux Kernel and for good reason. We would want native and direct communication
with hardware which is better for performance and being maintained and clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why did AMD use a HAL? Well, the simplest reason was for sharing code.
AMD&amp;rsquo;s software driver team is small. To save time, money, and effort, using
a HAL was a simple method. They could write code that (mostly) worked for
both Windows and Linux at the same time. So primary focus on Windows translated
to some focus on Linux. Unfortunately, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it worked well.
We all remember how &amp;ldquo;lovely&amp;rdquo; fglrx was at times with broken crossfire support,
broken eyefinity setup, poor kernel support, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK so small software dev team, HAL isn&amp;rsquo;t fully working in this instance,
what is the solution? They decided to go open source. Great, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t this
be simple? Short answer, No. They have to go over code with a fine tooth comb
to make sure they aren&amp;rsquo;t releasing code they &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t own&amp;rdquo; persay. Can&amp;rsquo;t exactly
opensource DirectX related etc. After that, they also have to remove the HAL and recreate
code from scratch to make a native/direct communication line for the Linux kernel.
You could say this is essentially rewriting the driver from scratch. Its also
more than just a display driver. You have Vulkan, OpenCL, HSA, VCE, UVD and the many
other interfaces in which one may use the graphics card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when can we expect to see support for all items the display code brings us?
Thats an excellent, but daunting question.
AMD is about to meet the crossroads in which they either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not support their latest graphics cards and APUs, VEGA and beyond, upon release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push their team to get the DAL/HAL converted and submitted to the Linux kernel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ALL of the above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure is on. They know they need support for their latest graphics chipsets, but
anything VEGA and beyond requires the new display code to even work on Linux. I suspect
we may not see working VEGA on AMDGPU (non-PRO), at least, until the end of the year.
Thats cutting it close if AMD expects to sell raven ridge APUs at the end of this year.
I could be proven wrong, but who knows? Kernel release cycles are consistantly about
&lt;a href=&#34;https://kernelnewbies.org/LinuxVersions&#34;&gt;70 days apart&lt;/a&gt;, so 2 kernel releases could be Dec of this year.
This massive change could be right on time to at least have some basics working.
4.13-dev already is seeing tons of &lt;a href=&#34;https://git.kernel.org/pub/scm/linux/kernel/git/next/linux-next.git/commit/?h=next-20170623&amp;amp;id=04d4fb5fa63876d8e7cf67f2788aecfafc6a28a7&#34;&gt;raven code&lt;/a&gt; being dropped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-now-and-what-about-gamers&#34;&gt;What about now and what about gamers?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll be happy to know you&amp;rsquo;re not forgotten. Mesa+AMDGPU has been gearing
itself up for supporting gamers. In fact since the opensource community has
gotten its hands on AMDGPU, its outperforming AMDGPU-PRO in several instances.
Is the opensource driver perfect? No, far from it, but its growing by leaps
and bounds at an accelerated rate. Even Valve has dedicated some resources
to assisting in the growth of AMDGPU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about Vulkan support? Its there. AMDGPU has radv which is also growing
quickly. radv is the radeon opensource vulkan project. Have you tried DOTA2
with vulkan lately? It works. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=article&amp;amp;item=amdgpu-new-1710&amp;amp;num=1&#34;&gt;See the benchmarks and gaming results here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valve has also offered its services to help forward AMDGPU. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;amp;px=AMDGPU-PRO-VR-Linux&#34;&gt;Looking forward to VR.&lt;/a&gt;
Virtual Reality is becoming big in gaming and soon Linux thanks to Valve.
Valve has also shown support for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gamingonlinux.com/articles/steamos-updated-valve-drops-amdgpu-pro-for-mesa.9712/page=2&#34;&gt;MESA&lt;/a&gt; only setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-how-does-this-affect-sabayon&#34;&gt;So how does this affect Sabayon?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, you&amp;rsquo;re going to notice the obvious, HDMI/DP Audio may not work yet,
no freesync, no HDMI 2.0, no VEGA and beyond, Vulkan support may be hit
and miss. If you&amp;rsquo;re using an HD7XXX or R9 2XX card, your drivers may change
after a kernel upgrade resulting in different behavior. People looking
for AMDGPU-PRO should and probably would abandon that thought considering
the performance gaming-wise is better off on the open source driver.
You may also have noticed the bump in MESA lately to 17.1? MESA may get
bumped more frequently due to the constant development for AMDGPU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand you may feel some frustration in this time awaiting fixes,
but please be aware this issue is affecting all Linux distributions.
Its the typical growing pains of Linux when a large change takes place.
We are keeping on top of it and trying to stay up-to-date bringing fixes,
and performance boosts, but maintaining stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you&amp;rsquo;re enjoying Sabayon just as much as we do!
-Frosty&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;have-you-considered-donating-yet-help-us-donate-donate-today&#34;&gt;Have you considered donating yet? Help us! &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sabayon.org/donate&#34;&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; today!&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
